<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Felix Schönbrodt</title>
<link>https://www.nicebread.de/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.nicebread.de/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Academic Website of Felix Schönbrodt</description>
<image>
<url>https://quarto.org/quarto.png</url>
<title>Felix Schönbrodt</title>
<link>https://www.nicebread.de/posts.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>My personal reviewing policy: No more billion-dollar donations</title>
  <dc:creator>Felix Schönbrodt</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.nicebread.de/posts/reviewing_policy.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<hr>
<!--Include academic icons or bottons-->
<!-- 
Load Academicons v1: https://jpswalsh.github.io/academicons/
-->
<p><link rel="stylesheet" href="https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/gh/jpswalsh/academicons@1/css/academicons.min.css"></p>
<p><link rel="stylesheet" href="http://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/font-awesome/4.3.0/css/font-awesome.min.css"></p>
<!---
The following code are needed to show dimension citation and altmetrics.
https://api.altmetric.com/embeds.html
https://badge.dimensions.ai/
--->
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js"></script>
<script async="" src="https://badge.dimensions.ai/badge.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="//cdn.plu.mx/widget-popup.js"></script>
<p><img src="https://www.nicebread.de/posts/img/burning_money.jpg" alt="Descriptive alt text" class="float-right" style="height: 300px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>I get more requests to review scientific papers than I can reasonably handle<sup>1</sup>. Hence, I have to decide which requests I accept and which I decline.</p>
<p><strong>I want to invest my reviewing work in research that is worth to be reviewed. Furthermore, I do not want to further increase the <a href="https://link.springer.com/epdf/10.1186/s41073-021-00118-2?sharing_token=UeRgaB3yWmGNtySWmnLpGG_BpE1tBhCbnbw3BuzI2RPBO8Gcbah4wDtGKkyO_SPjxA1xWygsV0WJsSTIiIMtEQUv_oxvHQpSSOwqSSBg2lOTlHUXLGEd-n36oU__EwOevZjGPTpEEfQTpUmyNjIKENS7AFgG05ZGj6HiC-oTHTE%3D">billion dollar donations</a> to premium publishers any more.</strong></p>
<p>When deciding whether to accept or reject a review, I apply the following heuristics:</p>
<section id="input-filter-i-decline-to-review-manuscripts-that-fail-these-checks" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="input-filter-i-decline-to-review-manuscripts-that-fail-these-checks">Input filter: I decline to review manuscripts that fail these checks</h3>
<ul>
<li><ol type="A">
<li>As a signatory of the Peer Reviewer’s Openness (PRO) initiative and the Commitment to Research Transparency, I expect open data and open material in each paper that I am supposed to review, or a public justification why it is not possible. I do not review manuscripts that fail this check.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><ol start="2" type="A">
<li>I signed the The Cost of Knowledge pledge, which means that I do not review for (or submit to) Elsevier journals.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><ol start="3" type="A">
<li>I reject, if the topic is not within my area of expertise (at least partially).</li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="weighting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weighting">Weighting</h3>
<p>After these initial eligibility checks, I apply the following weights:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reviews for funders</strong>. This is the category where I probably can have the strongest impact on research quality. Furthermore, often the funding of ECRs depends on a timely review, so I rarely reject these.</li>
<li>The most useful (and rewarding) manuscript reviews for me are <strong>Registered Reports</strong> (RRs), as my review can have the most constructive impact. Even better is the <a href="https://rr.peercommunityin.org/">PCI Registered Reports</a> initiative, as reviews are always published upon acceptance, and submitting authors are not tied to a specific journal.</li>
<li>Next, I’ll allocate my reviewing and editorial work primarily to <a href="https://www.fairopenaccess.org/">Fair Open Access</a> journals, such as <a href="https://open.lnu.se/index.php/metapsychology/about">Meta-Psychology</a>. I have no interest of devoting my publicly paid working time (or even unpaid evening hours) to boost the “premium” publisher’s <a href="https://alexholcombe.wordpress.com/2015/05/21/scholarly-publisher-profit-update/">ridiculous profit margin</a> even more.</li>
<li>I want reviews to be open, also as way to reduce redundancy. So much intellectual work goes into reviews, just to get hidden and often ignored. I prioritize journals that have an open peer review policy (such as <a href="https://open.lnu.se/index.php/metapsychology/about">Meta-Psychology</a> or <a href="https://online.ucpress.edu/collabra">Collabra</a>). As products of scholarly activity, open reviews should be citable with a doi, as, for example, Meta-Psychology does.</li>
<li>Although I increasingly aim to publish my own papers in fair OA journals, there sometimes is no good thematic match for my papers (yet). Therefore, I will still submit some of my work to „traditional“ journals (except Elsevier). For fairness and „paying back“, I will do at least 3 reviews for each paper that I submit to such a journal. Hopefully, more and more diamond OA journals will be established that allow choosing one with a thematic fit.</li>
</ul>
<p>I anticipate that my criteria will gradually shift more and more to the top categories.</p>
<p>I realize that this personal policy has some side effects. For example, I really appreciate the good work of the editorial team from Nature Human Behavior. They did a lot to improve standards and policies at a Nature journal. So, while I’d be happy to support that specific team, I do not want to support SpringerNature as a profit organization; even more as they now test a scheme where they take a „a non-refundable fee of €2,190 to cover an editorial assessment and the peer-review process“ (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-03324-y">Nature journals reveal terms of landmark open-access option</a>).</p>
<p>Wait – reviewers now get paid for their work? No, of course not. Researchers still do the reviews for free, as always. Nature now wants to get paid for your reviews.</p>
<p>I hope that with that reviewing policy I can make a small change towards a more open, more credible, and more efficient academic system. At least I feel much better with these priorities and have more fun reviewing.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I employ the following heuristic: To keep the current academic system going, I have to review three papers for each paper that I submit as first author (including all revisions, as they usually require additional reviews). I clearly exceed this heuristic a lot.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.nicebread.de/posts/reviewing_policy.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://www.nicebread.de/posts/img/burning_money.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
